Okay today's דף daf is גיטין ס"ט Gittin Samech Tet 69. We're
in the middle of a major discussion of various רפואות, refuot, various
remedies, health treatments that the גמרא Gemara is lining out because the
משנה Mishnah deals with a certain with a personality. And we pick
up after a fascinating אגדתא agadata relating to שלמה המלך Shlomo HaMelech
and אשמדאי. Ashmedai. And we are now ס"ח עמוד ב' Samech Chet
Amud Bet and we are five lines from the bottom.
לדמא דריישא, L'dama d'reisha, okay if a person has blood in the
head.
לייתי שורבינא ובינא ואסא Leiti shorvina u'vina va'asa
ואסא דרא, va'asa dara, excuse me, and fresh myrtle, וזיתא וחילפא v'zaita
v'chilfa and olives and poplar, this is all thanks to the translations
of
Koren, וחילפי דימא v'chilfi de-yama and sea willow, ויבלא v'yavla and cynodon,
who knows what that is. ולישלקונו בהדי הדדי, V'lishlakunu bahadi hadade, okay
and boil them all together. ולינטול תלת מאה כסי אהאי גיסא דריישא
V'lintol tlat me-ah kasei ahai gisa de-reisha and pour 300 cups on
one side of the head, or literally take 300 cups but pour
them apparently from one side of the head and ותלת מאה כסי
אהאי גיסא דריישא v'tlat me-ah kasei ahai gisa de-reisha and 300 cups
on the other side of the head. ואי לא, V'ei lo, and
if that's not effective, לייתי ורדא חיורא leiti varda chivra you should
go ahead and bring a white rose, ורד, vered, דקאי בחד דרא
de-kai bechad dara that all are on one row, the way Rashi
sort of says it means all the leaves all the excuse me
the petals are on one
side, דקאי בחד דרא de-kai bechad dara ולישלקהו v'lishlokei and go ahead
and boil it. ולינטול שיתין כסי אהאי גיסא דריישא V'lintol shitin kasei
ahai gisa de-reisha and pour 60 cups of this mixture on one
side of the head and ושיטין כסי אהאי גיסא דריישא v'shitin kasei
ahai gisa de-reisha and 60 cups on the other on the other
side of the head. Okay.
Now that's what you do for this blood ailment.
לצילחתא, L'tzilchata, now לצילחתא l'tzilchata for a like a strong headache or
Rashi says a pain in half of the head, Koren translates this
as a migraine. לייתי תרנגול ברא Leiti tarnagol bara you should take
a wild rooster, ולישחטיה בזוזא חיורא v'lishchatei be-zuza chivra and you should
slaughter it with a silver
זוז, zuz, a coin, I guess a sharpened coin, a white one,
which is Rashi says means silver,
pure silver. אהוא גיסא דכאיב ליה Ahu gisa de-kaiv leh and you
should שחט shacht this right by the side of the head where
you're having this pain. וניזדהר מדמיה דלא לסמייה לעיניה V'nizdahar me-damei de-lo
lismiyeh l'einei and you should be careful that the blood doesn't get
into your eyes, it will blind you. ולתליה בסיפי דבבא V'litlyeh be-sipei
de-vava
and hang it on the doorpost of the house, דכי עייל חייף
ביה de-chi ayil chayif beih that when you go into your house
you'll rub up against it, וכי נפיק חייף ביה v'chi nafik chayif
beih and when you leave your house you will rub up against
it and somehow that rubbing will help it. Okay top of ס"ט
עמוד א'. Samech Tet Amud Aleph. לפרוקיתא, L'frukita, if somebody has an
eye disease, Rashi says דקרו תילא de-karu tila whatever that is,
and presumably that's like a type of a cataracts I think or
something like that. לייתי עקרבא דשב חומרי Leiti akrava de-shav chumre you
should go ahead and take a scorpion, a seven-colored scorpion, Rashi says
it means a very old
one. וניבשיה בטולא V'niyabshei be-tula and dry it out in the shade.
ונישחוק תרתי מנא כוחלא V'nishchok tartei mana kuchla and you should go
ahead and grind together two portions of this כוחלא kuchla which is
this type of a thing that they used to put in the
eye,
וחדא מנא מיניה v'chada mana mineih so two portions of כוחלא kuchla
and one portion of this ground up scorpion.
I actually had a student once who was looking for alternative remedies
for Bell's palsy and he had somebody recommended for him this healer
to use a tea ran through a teabag, hot water ran through
a teabag of desiccated scorpion. So there you go. Interesting הלכה halacha
questions because scorpion isn't kosher. But here you're not drinking it. Okay
so anyway so you go ahead and have two portions of this
כוחלא kuchla and one portion of the
scorpion. וחדא מנא מיניה V'chada mana mineih ולימלי תלתא מכחלי בהאי עינא
v'limlei tlata machalei be-hai aina and you should take three applications, eyebrushes
full in one eye, ותלתא מכחלי בהאי עינא v'tlata machalei be-hai aina
and three brushes full in the other eye. טפי לא לימלי Tfai
lo limlei and you should not put any more in the eye,
דלא פקע עינא de-lo paka aina because if you do too much
your eye will burst. לשברירי דליליא, L'shavrire de-leilya,
now for blindness of the night. And the גמרא Gemara sometimes has
interesting incantations for שברירי shavrire if people might remember from ברכות. Berachot.
Anyway for night blindness, נייתי שודרא ברקא neiti shudra barka you should
go ahead and bring a rope of animal hair, וניסר חד כרעא
מיניה וחד
כרעא מכלבא v'nisar chad kera mineih v'chad kera me-kalba and tie one
of your legs with one end of the rope and one leg
to a dog. rope and one leg to the leg of a
dog וניטרפי ינוקי חספא בתריה venitrafei yanuki chaspa basrei
and a child should bang on a piece of
pottery walking
you know following you or throw the pieces of pottery at you
and say to him אסא כלבא אכסא תרנגולא asa kalba akasa tarnegola
that and they should say you know the dog is old and
the rooster is foolish.
So Rashi says that they're doing this as they're banging on the
pottery.
So where are we? Hold on. ולישבק שבע אומצי משבעה בתי velishbok
sheva umtzi misheva batei and should go ahead and take seven pieces
of raw meat from seven houses וליספנהו ניהליה בצינורא דדשא velispinehu nihalei
betzinura dedasha and the owners of these houses should put these pieces
of meat in the socket of the you know of the door
הצנורא דדשא hatzinura dedasha וניכלינהו בקלקולי דמתא venichlinehu bekilkulei demata
and he should go ahead and take it and eat them in
like the dump of the city. בתר הכי basar hachi after this
ליפשוט שודרא ברקא lifshote shudra barka they should undo this you know
the rope of hair ונימרו הכי venimru hachi and say here שבריני
דפלוני בר פלוניתא shavrini deploni bar plonisa this blindness of you know
so and so the son of so and so mother's name שבקיה
לפלוני בר פלוניתא shavkiyeh leploni bar plonisa should leave you know Reuven
bar Rachel וליכרו לכלבא בבבא דעיניה velichro lekalba bebaba deinei and should
go ahead and blow it into the eyes of the dog and
to the pupils of the dog. All right, so clearly there's some
type of an incantation, you know, even the Gemara presumably did not
believe that this was all medical science. There was some type of
a whatever you know incantation and other types of things that were
you know maybe brought about by שדים shedim was the belief in
something of that nature. Okay,
where were we? Hold on. לשיברי
דמי leshavrei dyami now day blindness לייתי שבעה סומקי מגוא דחיותא leisei
shiva sumkei migu dechayusa you should go ahead and take seven animal
spleens from the you know and from the innards of the animals
וניטוינהו אחספא דאומנא venitvinehu achaspa deumna
and you should go ahead and roast them on the pottery of
a bloodletter, the pot that was you know that used to collect
the blood וליתיב איהו מגוא ואינש אחרינא מאבראי veliseiv ihu migu ve-inish
achrina me-avrai
and the patient you know the person should sit on the inside
of the house and another person on the outside of the house
ולימא ליה velima lei and say the following
and I mean the person with the illness should say אבירא avira
and say the blind person the person with the blindness should say
הולי דאיכול havli de-ichul give to me you know okay hold on
a second. Yeah, the blind man should say to the person sitting
on the outside who does not have this blindness give me give
me and I will eat הולי דאיכול havli de-ichul ונימא ליה הך
פתיחא סב איכול venima lei hach pesicha sav ichul and the person
that is not blind should say to him here take and eat.
And
there's a question whether the word אבירא avira or פתיחא pesicha goes
in the quote marks or not in the quote marks. They say
blind man or the other person say seeing man or does the
seeing man say. Anyway, ובתר דאכל uvatar de-achal and after he eats
this meat these spleens so here by the way you're obviously ליטברה
לחספא litberah lechaspa let him break the pottery דאי לא de-i lo
because if he doesn't do this הדר עילויה hadar iluyei it'll come
back on him. Okay, very nice. לדמא דאתי מנחירי ledama de-asi minichiri
for a nosebleed blood that's coming out of a nostril לייתי גברא
כהן דשמיה לוי leisei gavra kohen deshmiya levi a person a Kohen
but whose name is Levi should go ahead and he should be
brought וליכתוב ליה לוי למפריע velichtov lei levi lemafriya
and he should write out the word לוי Levi backwards. ואי לא
ve-i lo and if that doesn't do anything ואי לא ve-i lo
if that doesn't work לייתי איניש מעלמא leisei inish mealma just take
a normal man וליכתוב ליה velichtov lei and he should write to
this normal man אנא פפי שילא בר סומקי למפריע ana papi shila
bar sumkei lemafriya
the following phrase he says I am Papi Shila bar Sumkei and
he should write that out backwards. ואי לא ve-i lo and if
somehow that did not work נכתוב ליה הכי nichtov lei hachi
he should write the following אטון דלי במי כסף aton deli bemei
chasaf taste from a bucket in
silver water אטון דלי במי פגם aton deli bemei pgam
and taste from a you know taste from a bucket in tinted
water in water that's spoiled. ואי לא ve-i lo and if somehow
that writing did not do the trick לייתי עקרא דאספסא leisei ikra
de-aspasa
he should go ahead and take the root of fodder ואשלא דפורייא
עתיקא ve-ashla depuraya atika and a rope of that's used for a
for a bed an old bed וקורטסא vekurtasa and a and and
some type of a paper, ומוריקי u-moriki and saffron, וסומקא דלולא דליבא
ve-sumka de-lula de-liba and the red of a palm branch, a palm
tree, וניקלינהו בהדי הדדי ve-niklinhu badei hadadei burn these all together, ולייתי
גבבא דעמרא ve-leiti gevava de-amra and he should go ahead and take
a, you know, like a cluster of wool, וניגדו תרתי פתילתא ve-nigdo
tartei p'silsa and he should like and he should spin two threads
from this wool, ולטמשה בחלא ve-litmish be-chala
and soak it in vinegar, וניגבייהו בקטמא הדין ve-nigveihu be-kitma hadein and
roll it into the ashes of this whole concoction he just burned,
וניסיה בניחירי ve-nisei bi-nechirei and then stick that up his nostrils, so
here you at least see something that's going in his nostrils. ואי
לא ve-i lo and if that doesn't work, ליחזי אמת המים דאזלא
ממזרח כלפי מערב leichezi amat ha-mayim de-azla mi-mizrach klapei maarav he should
go and see a, you know, a conduit of water that is
going from east to west, a stream of water, ממזרח כלפי מערב,
mi-mizrach klapei maarav, וניפסע ve-nifsa and he should step over it, וניקום
חד כרעא להאי גיסא וחד כרעא להאי גיסא ve-neikum chad kara le-hai
gisa ve-chad kara le-hai gisa one leg on one side of this
stream and one on the other, ונישקול טינא בידיה דיימינא ve-nishkol tina
b'yadei de-yamina and he should go ahead and he should hold on
to
a piece of clay with his right hand, מתותי כרעא דשמאלא mi-tosei
kara de-smala
he should hold it with his right hand and he should put
it under his left arm, ובידיה דשמאלא מתותי כרעא דיימינא u-v'yadei de-smala
mi-tosei kara de-yamina and take a similar piece of clay in his
left hand and hold it under his right arm, וניגדול תרתי פתילתא
דעמרא ve-nigdol tartei p'silsa de-imra and he should go ahead and spin
two threads of wool, וניטמש בטינא ve-nitmesh be-tina
and he should go ahead and submerge them in this type of
a clay or plaster, וניסיה בניחירי ve-nisei bi-nechirei and put it in
his ear, in his nose, excuse me, his nostrils. ואי לא ve-i
lo and if that didn't work, ליתיב תותי מרזבא leisiv tusei marzeva
let him go sit underneath a like a drainpipe, ולייתו מיא ve-leisu
maya and take water, ולישדו עליה ve-lishdu alei and pour the water
down the drainpipe and it should hit him, ולימרו ve-limru and he
should say, כי היכי ki heichi and then he should say, כי
היכי דפסק הני מיא ki heichi de-pasak hanei maya the same way
this water went down the drainpipe and then
stopped, ליפסוק דמיה דפלניא בר פלניתא lifsook dmei de-planya bar planisa the
blood of so-and-so, the son of so-and-so, should come to an end,
לדמא דאתי מפומא le-dama de-asei mi-puma okay fine, that's what you do
for a nosebleed. Now, לדמא דאתי מפומא le-dama de-asei mi-puma from if
blood comes from the mouth, בדקינן ליה בגילא דחיטתא badkinan lei be-gila
de-chitasa
we check him out with a
straw
of wheat, like we put a straw of wheat I guess into
his mouth to see what the nature of the problem is. So
we're actually going to do some test here, okay? So, אי סריך
ei sarich if the blood is viscous like
it's sticky, מריאה קאתי mi-reeya ka-asi then it is coming from the
lungs, ואית ליה תקנתא ve-is lei takanta and
then there's a way to heal it. ואי לא ve-i lo but
if it's not sticky, you know, if it's more liquidy, מכבדא קאתי
mi-kavda ka-asi then it's coming from the liver, ולית ליה תקנתא ve-leis
lei takanta there's no way to fix it. Alright, now we didn't
say yet what the way to fix it is, but we will.
אמר ליה רב אמי לרב אשי amar lei Rav Ami le-Rav Ashi
Rav Ami said to Rav Ashi, והנן איפכא תנן ve-anan ipcha tnan
one minute, you're saying that it's easier to heal when it comes
from the lung, but we taught the opposite in terms of the
treifa of an animal. ניטל הכבד ולא נשתייר הימנו כלום nital ha-kaved
ve-lo nishtayer heimenu klum if the liver is removed and there's nothing
left of the liver, then that's a טרפה. treifa. הריאה שניקבה ha-reeya
she-nikva או שחסרה o she-chasra but if the lung has a hole
in it or it's missing something, then that's also a טרפה. treifa.
So by the liver only if the entire liver is removed. So
how come you're saying the blood is coming from the liver it's
a bigger problem? It seems like, you know, if there's a problem
with the liver, the liver is more, you know, a person can
still live, an animal could still live even if there's a degree
of a problem with the liver. אמר ליה amar lei he said
back to him, כיון דמפומא קאתי keivan de-mi-puma ka-asi no,
no, no, that's true once you open up the animal and you
find that problem in the liver, so if you have a partial
liver you're okay, but here we have a guy who has blood
coming out of his mouth, אמור איתמוחי איתמח emor itmuchi itmach there
there's a concern now that the whole liver has dissolved and that's
why it's a problem. I don't know how it definitely is dissolved,
why do we say it definitely no healing, anyway, אמר מר amar
mar we said before, אי מריאה קאתי אית ליה תקנתא ei mi-reeya
ka-asi is lei takanta now if it is sticky then it's coming
from the lungs and therefore it can be fixed, it has some
type of a remedy. מאי תקנתיה mai takantei what's the remedy? לייתי
שבע מוני מפרמא דסילקא leiti sheva muni mi-farma de-silka
so he should bring seven like, you know, handfuls, fistfuls, of chopped
beet, ושבע
מוני פרמא דכרתי ve-sheva muni farma de-karti and seven handfuls of chopped
leek, וחמשה כוני פרדא ve-chamisha kuni frada and five, I
think I was
saying מוני, muni, כוני, kuni, וחמשה כוני פרדא. ve-chamisha kuni frada. רש״י
Rashi says it's a type of a grass.
Where are we? Hold on. ותלתא קוני דטלפחי ve-tlata kuni de-talpachi
and three handfuls of lentils, וקונא דכמונא ve-kuna de-kamuna
and a handful of cumin, וקונא דחבלי ve-kuna de-chavli
and one handful of rope, וכנגדן ve-negedan קינשא פטירתא kinsha petirta
and equal to that entire amount he should take the entrails of
a פטירא petira like
פטר רחם peter rechem of a firstborn animal. רש״י Rashi says entrails.
Okay, ולבשול ve-livshol
and cook it all together, וליכול ve-lechol and then eat it, ולישתי
בתריה ve-lishtei batrei and then drink afterwards שיכרא חריפא shichra charifa strong
type of
beer, דטבא de-tava good strong beer. Fine. That's what you do with
that ailment, blood from the lungs. לקוחא, Lekucha, now what happens if
you have a pain in your teeth? אמר רבה בר בר חנה,
Amar Rabba bar bar Chana, ליתי תומא יחידא, leiti tuma yechida, take
a single garlic. רש״י Rashi says it's like if only one clove
of garlic grew in a bulb. I don't know how you get
that. Anyway, ונמרסיה במשחא ומלחא ve-nirmasei be-mishcha u-melcha
and you should go ahead
and pound it, grind it into olive oil and salt, ונישפיה אטופרא
דאליונא דההוא גיסא ve-nishfyei a-tufra de-alyona de-hahu gisa
and you should go ahead and put it on the thumbnail
of the side that hurts him, דההוא גיסא דכאיב ליה, de-hahu gisa
de-kaiv lei,
ונהדרה ליה גדנפא ve-nahadra lei gadanfa and then let him surround it,
so you've got it on your left thumb or whatever it
is, ונהדרה ליה גדנפא דלישא ve-nahadra lei gadanfa de-lisha and then surround
it with a rim
of dough, וניזהר לבישריה דקשי לחיורא ve-nizhar le-vishrei de-kashi le-chivra
and he should be very careful that it doesn't actually touch his
flesh because then it would cause, could cause boils. Okay. חינכי, Chinchei,
now how about a problem with the gums? אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Yochanan, חומסי, chumsei,
so Rabbi Yochanan says כימאמרו, ke-mamru, so you should take this חומסי
chumsei which is like the מאמרו mamru plant. Okay. ועיקרא דחומסי ve-ikra
de-chumsei and you should take the root of this חומסי chumsei whatever
that is,
עדיף ממאמרו adif mi-mamru and if you actually get the root of
the plant, that's even better than מאמרו. mamru. Okay. So you take
this plant which is similar to this מאמרו. mamru. וננקוט בפומה ve-ninkot
be-pumei
and put it in your mouth. Okay, הני לאוקמי, hanei le-ukmei,
that is in order to cause it to not spread, to cause
the problem with the gums. לבשולי, Le-vshulei, however, if you actually want
to boil them, meaning רש״י Rashi sort of says like to get
the pus to gather so that you can burst it, ליתי פארי
דריש נאפיא, leiti parei de-reish nafya, then you should go ahead and
take
the bran that's at the upper part of a sieve when you
sift grain, you should take the bran, וטלפחי ve-talpachi and lentils, באפרייהו
be-afraihu with the dirt that they came from, ותבלוליתא ve-tavlulita
and also this תבלוליתא tavlulita
which is apparently fenugreek, וחומסתא דכשותא ve-chumasta de-chashuta
and this חומסתא דכשותא chumasta de-chashuta which is apparently some type of
a piece of the hop plant, וננקוט כגוזא בפומה ve-ninkot ke-guza be-pumei
and you should take the amount of this that's like the size
of a nut and put it in your mouth. Now that gets
the pus to gather. Now let's say you want to open the
blister. לפתוחי, Liftochi, if you want to open it, לינפח ליה חבריה
תחלי חיוורתא, linpach lei chavrei tachli chivarta,
so now you use like a pea shooter, your friend should blow
like a white seed, בגילא דחיטתא be-gila de-chitteta
through a straw of wheat. You use like a pea shooter and
that I guess hits the thing and causes it to burst.
Okay, so now it burst. Now you want it to scab and
heal. לאסוקי, Le-asokei, so if you want it to heal, ליתי עפרא
מטולא דבי כסי, leiti afra mi-tula de-vei kasei, go ahead and take
some dirt that was in the shade of an
outhouse, וניגבל בדושא ve-nigbal be-dusha and knead it together with
honey, וניכול ve-nechol and eat it, דמעלי ליה de-ma'ali lei because that
will be good for you.
Now, לבירסם, Le-virsam, now if you're dealing with בירסם birsam which רש״י
Rashi says it's some type of an illness that comes to the
head through the nose, ליתי כי אפיקתא דנישתור, leiti ki apikta de-nishtur,
you should go ahead. and take a
nut-sized amount of נשדור, nishtor, which apparently Jastrow says is ammonia. רש"י
Rashi says אמוניקא. ammonica. Okay, וכי אגוזא דחלביניתא, ve-chi agoza de-chalbinisa,
and you should also take a nut-sized amount of galbanum, of galbanum,
דחלביניתא דושנא, de-chalbinisa dushana, sweet galbanum, excuse
me, ומלי תרבדא דובשא, u-mali tarvada duvsha,
and a full amount of a spoonful of honey דחיורא de-chivra of
white honey, ומלי נטלא בת מחוזא חמרא, u-mali natla bat mechuza chamra,
and a and a full amount of, you know, and a ומלי
נטלא בת מחוזא חמרא, mali natla bat mechuza chamra, and a vessel
that comes from Mechuza, בת מחוזא bat mechuza maybe was a whatever,
was a certain רש"י Rashi says it was a it contained a
רביעית, revi'is, like three ounces of wine נקידא nekida of, you know,
of like clear wine, ונישלקינהו בהדי הדדי ve-nishalkinhu bahadi hadadi and cook
them all together.
וכי בשיל נשדור, ve-chi bashil nishtor, and when the ammonia is boiled,
בשיל כולהו, bashil kulhu, then everything will be boiled because that one
takes the longest to boil. ואי לא, ve-i lo, and if that
didn't work, ליתי רביעתא דחלבא דעיזא, leisi revi'asa de-chalba de-iza, go ahead
and take a רביעית revi'is of milk from a white goat, חלבא
דעיזא חיורתא chalba de-iza chivrasa of white goat, milk of white goat,
דף ס"ט עמוד ב'. daf samech tes amud bais. וניטרפי אתלתא קלחי
כרובא, ve-nitrafei atalasa kalchi keruva, and go ahead and stir it or
dip
it into it three stalks of a of
cabbage, of
קלחי כרובא. kalchi keruva. ונכמשי בגוויה, ve-nichmashei be-gaveih, and stir it בגבזא
דמהרמין, be-gavza de-maharmin, and stir it with a
spoon with a twig of מהרמין, maharmin, of מהרמין, maharmin, which apparently
is is marjoram. Okay, וכי בשיל גבזא במהרמין, ve-chi bashil gavza be-maharmin,
בשיל כולהו, bashil kulhu, and when the marjoram is boiled then it'll
all be boiled. ואי לא, ve-i lo, and if that didn't work,
ליתי נפקא דכלבא חיורא, leisi nafka de-kalba chivra, go take the excrement
of a dog, a white dog, וניגבל בנטפא, ve-nigbal be-natfa, and go
ahead and mix it
with with, you know, with balm.
וכמה דאפשר נפקא לא
ניכול, ve-chama de-efshar nafka lo neichol, and as much as possible, נפקא
לא ניכול, nafka lo neichol, don't, you know, don't eat the feces,
I mean I don't know what you're supposed to do with it,
you went ahead and you mixed it with it, maybe you're supposed
to apply it or
something, you know, but or maybe it's just eat it but don't
eat too much of it, דמפרק לגירא, de-mifrak le-gira, because it actually
will cause a separation of the limbs. Okay,
fine. So now the Gemara continues, hold
on, that you do eat this excrement but that the Gemara was
saying if at possible try any other thing because if you try
this ailment, this remedy too much with the excrement, it could cause
this other problem. Okay, fine. Moving on, לגירא, le-gira, for a for
a stinging pain, ליתי גירא דלילתא, leisi gira de-lilasa, go take a
גירא, gira, גירא gira also means like an arrow, so you know,
go ahead and bring or a stone of Lilith. So what's a
stone of
Lilith? So רש"י Rashi says, you know, Lilith was obviously some type
of a shade or demon, but anyway it's some type of a
hailstone that looks like an arrow. ונפכיה, ve-nifcheih, turn it upside
down, which רש"י Rashi says means that the, you know, the point
of the arrow is facing towards the ground, ונשדי מיא עלויה ונשתי,
ve-nishdei maya ilveih ve-nishtei, and pour water over it and drink the
water. ואי לא, ve-i lo, and if that didn't work, ליתי ממיא
דאישתי מיניה כלבא בליליא, leisi mimaya de-ishtei mineih kalba be-leilya, take water
that a dog drank from it at
night, וניזדהר מגילויא, ve-nizdahar mi-giluya, and be very careful not to leave
that uncovered because even though normally you're not supposed to leave things
uncovered, you know, in this case maybe it's particularly dangerous. Okay, now
לגילויא, le-giluya, if you drank uncovered water in general which we know
is a problem, then אנפקא דחמרא חיא, anfaka de-chamra chaya, then the
way to fix it is to drink
a to drink a unit a log a whatever or a רביעית
revi'is of white wine, fine, undiluted wine. חיא, chaya, excuse me, not
white, that's chivra. חיא, chaya, raw wine, undiluted wine. Okay, למורסא, le-mursa,
for something like a blister, something filled with pus, אנפקא דחמרא באהלא,
anfaka de-chamra be-ahala, you go should take a drink a רביעית revi'is
of wine which is, you know,
which has been like a mixed with this plant דחמרא באהלא, de-chamra
be-ahala, אהלא, ahala, which is, you know,
אהלות. ahalos. Okay, excuse me,
oh wait, אהלא תולנא. ahala tulana. Okay, אהלא תולנא ahala tulana is
the name of the plant. So go ahead and have this wine
mixed with this plant אהלא תולנא. ahala tulana. Okay, לפרחא דליבא, le-pircha
de-liba, if you
have... Like a fluttering of the heart, לפירחא דליבא. Le-pircha de-liba. ליתי
תלתא ברושיאתא דשערי, Leisi tlasa brushiasa de-sa'arei, you could go and
take three loaves of
barley ונישתרינהו בכמכא ve-nishterinehu be-kamcha and you could go ahead and soak
them in כמכא, kimcha, which is this
type
of a yogurt type of a
thing, דלא עברו ליה ארבעין יומין, de-la avru lei arba'in yomin, that
is 40 days within the time from which it was made, וניכול
ve-neichol and eat it.
ונישתי בתריה חמרא מרקא Ve-nishti basrei chamra marka and drink afterwards, you
should drink diluted wine, mixed wine. אמר ליה רב אחא מדיפתי לרבינא,
Amar lei Rav Acha mi-Difti le-Ravina, Rav Acha of Difti said to
Ravina, וכל שכן דפארח ליביה, ve-chol sheken de-parach libei, wait a minute,
if you drink that stuff that'll cause more fluttering of the heart
because apparently that stuff, diluted wine, these are seen as light foods
and you want something that's a heavy food
that will because your heart to be more rooted and anchored.
אמר ליה אנא ליוקרא דליבא אמרי. Amar lei ana le-yukra de-liba amri.
You're right. I was actually, that apparently it was Ravina that was
saying all this stuff. I don't know, I lost track. But anyway
he's saying that remedy was if somebody has a heaviness of heart,
then you drink the diluted wine and that causes more lightness of
the heart. לפירחא דליבא, Le-pircha de-liba, if you have a lightness of
the heart, ליתי תלתא ברושיאתא דחיטי, leisi tlasa brushiasa de-chiti, then you
get heavier stuff. Three loaves of not of barley but of wheat,
ונישתרינהו בדובשא ve-nishterinehu be-duvsha and soak them not in this yogurt but
in honey. These are denser things. וניכול Ve-neichol and you should eat
it. ונישתי בתריה חמרא חיא. Ve-nishti basrei chamra chaya. Then you should
drink afterwards raw wine. Okay, so that's that. Now,
לצירכא דליבא, Le-tzircha de-liba, if you have a heart pain, ליתי תלתא
בייעי ניניא, leisi tlasa beiei ninya, you should take three egg worths
of mint, like nana, וביעתא דכמונא u-beia de-kamuna and one egg worth
of cumin, וביעתא דשומשמי u-beia de-shumshemi and one egg of sesame, וניכול
ve-neichol and eat it. Good. Okay, לכאב מיא, Le-chev maya, if you
have a stomach ache, ליתי תלת מאה פלפלי אריכתא, leisi tlasa mea
pilpali arichta, you should take 300 long peppers, וכל יומא נישתי מאה
מיניהו בחמרא, ve-chol yoma nishti mea mineihu be-chamra, and every day you
should drink, I don't know you drink a pepper, you cook it
in something, I don't know, you liquefy it, anyway, 100 of them
together with
wine, בחמרא. be-chamra. רבינא דמנרש עבד ליה לברתיה. Ravina de-Minrash avad lei
le-barteih. This person Ravina of Narsh, he made for his
daughter, לברתיה דרב אשי, le-barteih de-Rav Ashi, the daughter of Rav Ashi,
מאה וחמישין מהני דידן. me-a ve-chamishin me-hanei didan. He, rather than using
300 peppers, he only used 150 of our Babylonian peppers which maybe
were as powerful as 300 of Eretz
Yisroel pepper, ואיצייא ve-itzaya and she was healed.
Now, okay.
לכירצא, Le-chirtza, if you're going to deal with like a type of
kirtza which apparently is
roundworm, okay. אנפקא דחמרא באטרפא דערא, anpaka de-chamra be-atrefa de-ara, you should
drink a,
hold on one second,
you should drink like a revi'is of wine in
leaves, as Sanzino says or whatever, Kohut says it's laurel leaves.
לכירצא חיורא, Le-chirtza chivra, if you have this white type of
worm, ליתי ביזרא גלגלאי leisi bizra galglai וניצייריה בשיסטגא, ve-nitzayreih be-shistaga, you
should go ahead and bring cress and tie it in a piece
of
cloth, ונישייריה במיא ve-nishayreih be-maya and you should go ahead and then
soak it in water, ונישתי ve-nishti and drink it. וניזדהר מבינתא Ve-nizdar
mi-binta and you should be very careful
afterwards not with the
seed, דאי לא מינקבא ליה למעייניה, de-i la minkva lei le-ma'aineih, because
if you drink the seed or something it will go and puncture
your
intestine. למאסר. Le-maser. Now, how about if you basically
have diarrhea and you want to address
that? So what do you do? To maser from the word like
asir, to tie up, to bind up. You want to
stop the diarrhea.
סיסין רטיבא במיא. Sisin retiva be-maya. You should go ahead and take
sisin, which is chamomile apparently, when it's still wet in water and
eat that. למישרא, Le-mishra, if you want to do the opposite, not
to be oser but to be matir, if you have constipation and
you want to
relax the bowels, יבישא במיא. yevisha be-maya. You should go ahead and
take this chamomile but it should be dried and soaked in water
rather than wet and soaked in water. So dried out chamomile rather
than fresh chamomile.
וסימנך עיצא רטיבא דסכר נהרא. Ve-simanch itza retiva de-sachar nahara. And the
way to sort of
remember whether you use the wet or the dry is that wet
grass apparently is used to dam rivers. So if you want to
cause the constipation, then you want to go ahead and use the
fresh one. And if you want to cause the relaxation, you want
to use the dry one. Okay.
Now, לתחלא, Letechla, if you have something the matter with your
spleen, ליתי שבע בני דמיא, Leisi sheva bani de'maya, you should go
ahead and bring seven water leeches, yum yum, okay, וניבשיהו בטולא, veniyavshinu
betula, and dry them out in the shade, וכל יומא נשתי תרתי
ותלתא בחמרא, vechol yoma nishiti tartei veslasa bechamra, and every day you
should, and each day you should drink two and a third with
wine. Now some of these things here are not exactly kosher. I
mean before we were talking about animal intestines or whatever, but I
suppose the animal could be shechted properly. A dog excrement is not
technically not kosher. But anyway, these are not kosher, but again, these
are seen as really dangerous illnesses, you know, possibly סכנת נפשות, sakanas
nefashos, and this is what the Gemara
believed were the remedies. Okay. So drink two and a third each
day for three days with wine, וכל יומא נשתי תרתי ותלתא בחמרא.
vechol yoma nishiti tartei veslasa bechamra. ואי לא, Ve'ei lo, and if
that didn't work, ליתי תחלא דצפירתא, leisi techla detzifirta, you should go
ahead and take the spleen of a female goat, דלא איפתח, delo
iftach, that never gave birth,
ונתחייה בתנורא, venis'chayei betanura, and you should go ahead and place it
in the oven, dry it out in the oven, ונוקיה להדה, venokei
lahadei, and stand by across from it, near it, ונימא הכי היכי
דיביש האי תחלא, veneima hachi heichi deyavish hai techla, and say the
way this spleen is now drying out in the oven, נייבש תחלא
דפלוני בר פלוניתא, niyavesh techla deploni bar plonisa, the spleen of so-and-so
the son of so-and-so should be dried out. Okay. ואי לא, Ve'ei
lo, and if that didn't work,
נתחייה ביני אורבי, nis'chayei beinei urvei, you should go ahead and place
this goat spleen between the bricks
of, דביתא חדתא, debeisa chadsa, a new house, ונימא הכין, veneima hachin,
and say the following, say the same thing. The same way this
is going to be dried out, you know, my spleen should be
dried out. ואי לא, Ve'ei lo, and if that didn't work, ליבקי
שכבא דשכיב בשבתא, livki shichva deshichiv beshabsa, you should go ahead and
find a somebody who died on
Shabbos, ונשקליה לידיה, venishkalei liyadei, and hold on to his
hand,
ונוספה אתחלא, venosfei ateclha, and place the hand of this dead person
on your spleen, on the spleen of the person who's ill, ונימא
הכי היכי דיביש האי ידא, veneima hachi heichi deyavish hai yada, and
say the same way this hand has dried, נייבש תחלא דפלוני
בר פלוניתא, niyavesh techla deploni bar plonisa, the spleen of so-and-so son
of so-and-so, meaning my spleen, should dry. ואי לא, Ve'ei lo, and
if that didn't work, נייתי ביניתא, neisi binisa, you should go ahead
and take a fish, ונתבגא בי נפחא, venisavgei bei nafcha, and you
should go ahead and roast it at the, you know, in the
house of a blacksmith, וניכלה במיא דבי נפחא, venichlei bemaya debei nafcha,
and eat it from the water that ran off from the house
of the blacksmith, ונישתי ממיא דבי נפחא, venishti mimaya debei nafcha, and
you should go ahead
and drink that water. I'm not sure between eat it with the
water and drink the water, but maybe okay, two separate things. Okay.
ההיא עיזא דהוה שתיא מיא דבי נפחא, hahi iza dehavas shesya maya
debei nafcha,
now,
you know, there was a certain goat that drank the water from
that ran off from the blacksmith's
factory, אישתחיט ולא אישתכח לה תחלא, ishtachit velo ishtakach la techla, and
when it was shechted, it had no spleen. So this will definitely
cause the spleen to dry out. ואי לא, Ve'ei lo, and if
that didn't work, ליפתח חביתא דחמרא לשמיה, liftach chavita dechamra lishmei, you
should open up a new barrel of wine, you know, for your,
for the sake of the sick person, meaning like you should drink
a lot of wine. אמר ליה רבא בריה דרב לרב אשי, amar
lei rava brei de'rav l'rav ashi, Rava said, אי אית ליה חביתא
דחמרא לא אתי לקמיה דמר, ei is lei chavisa dechamra lo asi
lekamei demar, if this person had a whole barrel of wine, he
wouldn't have come for you for the remedy. Meaning if he had,
apparently wine was a definite good cure, but you needed a lot
of it. And if this person had that type of money, you
know, he would not have had to seek out other remedies to
be able to do this.
אלא מרגלא בפת שחרית דמעלי לכולי גופיה, ela margla bepas shachris demalyi
lechulei gufei, but rather, a person what another thing a person can
do is to eat just,
you know, have a bread in the morning and that will be
good for your whole body, meaning that might just be an advice
for like general health. Okay. לרושחתא, lerushchasa, I you know I think
we will stop over here. Okay.